{"test_questions": [[{"question": "S1:\nIn the middle of one side of the square sits the Chairman of the committee, the most important person in the room.\n\n\nP :\nFor a committee is not just a mere collection of individuals.\n\n\nQ :\nOn him rests much of the responsibility for the success or failure of the committee.\n\n\nR :\nWhile this is happening we have an opportunity to get the 'feel' of this committe.\n\n\nS :\nAs the meeting opens, he runs briskly through a number of formalities.\n\n\nS6:\nFrom the moment its members meet, it begins to have a sort nebulous life of its own.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "PQRS", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA force of exists between everybody in the universe.\n\n\nP :\nNormally it is very small but when the one of the bodies is a planet, like earth, the force is considerable.\n\n\nQ :\nIt has been investigated by many scientists including Galileo and Newton.\n\n\nR :\nEverything on or near the surface of the earth is attracted by the mass of earth.\n\n\nS :\nThis gravitational force depends on the mass of the bodies involved.\n\n\nS6:\nThe greater the mass, the greater is the earth's force of attraction on it. We can call this force of attraction gravity.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRQS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QSPR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nCalcutta unlike other cities kepts its trams.\n\n\nP :\nAs a result there horrendous congestion.\n\n\nQ :\nIt was going to be the first in South Asia.\n\n\nR :\nThey run down the centre of the road\n\n\nS :\nTo ease in the city decided to build an underground railway line.\n\n\nS6:\nThe foundation stone was laid in 1972.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFor some time in his youth Abraham Lincoln was manager for a shop.\n\n\nP :\nThen a chance Customer would come.\n\n\nQ :\nYoung Lincoln way of keeping shop was entirely unlike anyone else's\n\n\nR :\nLincoln would jump up and attend to his needs and then revert to his reading.\n\n\nS :\nHe used to lie full length on the counter of the shop eagerly reading a book.\n\n\nS6:\nNever before had Lincoln had so much time for reading as had then.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAll the land was covered by the ocean.\n\n\nP :\nThe leading god fought the monster, killed it and chopped its body in to two halves.\n\n\nQ :\nA terrible monster prevented the gods from separating the land from the water.\n\n\nR :\nThe god made the sky out of the upper part of the body and ornamented it with stars.\n\n\nS :\nThe god created the earth from the lower part, grew plants on it and populated it with animals.\n\n\nS6:\nThe god moulded the first people out of clay according to his own image and mind.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSmoke oozed up between the planks.\n\n\nP :\nPassengers were told to be ready to quit the ship.\n\n\nQ :\nThe rising gale fanned the smouldering fire.\n\n\nR :\nEveryone now knew there was fire on board.\n\n\nS :\nFlames broke out here and there.\n\n\nS6:\nMost people bore the shock bravely.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nYou know my wife, Madhavi, always urged me to give up smoking.\n\n\nP :\nI really gave it up.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd so When I went to jail I said to myself I really must give it up, if for no other reason than of being self-reliant.\n\n\nR :\nWhen I emerged from jail, I wanted to tell her of my great triumph.\n\n\nS :\nBut when I met her, there she was with a packet of cigarettes.\n\n\nS6:\npoor girl!.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhen a satellite is launched, the rocket begins by going slowly upwards through the air.\n\n\nP :\nHowever, the higher it goes, the less air it meets.\n\n\nQ :\nAs the rocket goes higher, it travels faster.\n\n\nR :\nFor the atmosphere becomes thinner.\n\n\nS :\nAs a result there is less friction.\n\n\nS6:\nConsequently, the rocket still does not become too hot.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA father having offered to take the baby out in a perambulator, was tempted by the sunny morning to slip into a pub for a glass of beer.\n\n\nP :\nIndignant at her husband's behaviour, she decided to teach him a lesson.\n\n\nQ :\nShe wheeled away the pram.\n\n\nR :\nA little later, his wife came by, where to her horror, she discovered her sleeping baby.\n\n\nS :\nLeaving the pram outside, he disappeared inside the bar.\n\n\nS6:\nShe waited for him, anticipating the white face and quivering lips which would soon appear with the news that the baby had been stolen.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "SPQR", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe city is almost a slum and stinks most of time.\n\n\nP :\nThe slush on the road did not deter them.\n\n\nQ :\nThe occasional slips and falls were considered a small price to pay for the trip.\n\n\nR :\nThey were excited, fascinated by the sight of fresh snow on the roads.\n\n\nS :\nEven so, it looked beautiful to tourists of various categories.\n\n\nS6:\nBut some visitors came away with the unforgettable sight of young labours scantily clad.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nVenice is a strange and beautiful city in the north of Italy.\n\n\nP :\nThere are about four hundred old stone bridges joining the island of Venice.\n\n\nQ :\nIn this city there are no motor cars, no horses, no buses.\n\n\nR :\nThese small islands are near one another.\n\n\nS :\nIt is not an island but a hundred and seventeen islands.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is because Venice has no streets.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PRQS", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe Hound of Baskervilles was feared by the people of the area.\n\n\nP :\nSome people spoke of seeing a huge, shadowy form a Hound at midnight on the moor.\n\n\nQ :\nBut they spoke of it in tones of horror.\n\n\nR :\nNobody had actually seen the hound.\n\n\nS :\nThis shadowy form did not reveal any details about the animal.\n\n\nS6:\nThe Hound of Baskervilles remains an unsolved mystery.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPQR", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA gentleman who lived alone always had two plates placed on the table at dinner time.\n\n\nP :\nOne day just as he sat down to dine, the cat rushed in to the room.\n\n\nQ :\nOne plate was for himself and other was for his cat.\n\n\nR :\nshe drooped a mouse into her own plate and another into her master plate.\n\n\nS :\nHe used to give the cat a piece of meat from his own plate.\n\n\nS6:\nIn this way the cat showed her gratitude to her master.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSPR", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "RPQS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAnts eat worms, centipedes and spiders.\n\n\nP :\nThey are usually much quicker than the ant itself.\n\n\nQ :\nNevertheless, these animals do not make easy game for ants.\n\n\nR :\nBesides, they have an extraordinary number of ways of escaping.\n\n\nS :\nThey also eat larvae and insect adults such as flies, moths and spring tails.\n\n\nS6:\nSome jump, and some give out a pungent repellent substance.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "SRQP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSatyajit Ray made several films for children.\n\n\nP :\nLater film makers have followed his lead.\n\n\nQ :\nToday other nations are making the children's film in a big way.\n\n\nR :\nThis was at a time when no director considered children as potential audience.\n\n\nS :\nRay was, thus, a pioneer in the field.\n\n\nS6:\nBut today few think of Ray as a maker of children's films.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nHungary, with a population of about 10 million, lies between Czechoslovakia to the north and Yugoslavia to the south.\n\n\nP :\nHere a great deal of grain is grown.\n\n\nQ :\nIn recent years, however, progress has been made also in the field of industrialisation.\n\n\nR :\nMost of this country consists of an extremely fertile plain, through which the river Danube flows.\n\n\nS :\nIn addition to grain, the plain produces potatoes, sugar, wine and livestock.\n\n\nS6:\nThe new industries derive mainly from agricultural production.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "RQSP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPalaeobotany is the study of fossil plants preserved in rocks dating back in millions of years.\n\n\nP :\nRecords of the history of the world are contained in fossils.\n\n\nQ :\nThrough the ages, plants have evolved from simple to more complex forms.\n\n\nR :\nFirst there were water plants then land plants appeared during the Paleozoic era.\n\n\nS :\nBut since the fossil remains appear locked in rock layers, they are closely related to the geologist area of investigation.\n\n\nS6:\nThe fossil plants indicate the age of the rock, and also point to facts regarding climate, temperature and topography.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOn vacation in Tangier, Morocco, my friend and I sat down at a street cafe.\n\n\nP :\nAt one point, he bent over with a big smile, showing me, a single gold tooth and a dingy fez.\n\n\nQ :\nsoon I felt the presence of someone standing alongside me.\n\n\nR :\nBut this one wouldn't budge.\n\n\nS :\nWe had been cautioned about beggars and were told to ignore them.\n\n\nS6:\nFinally a man walked over to me and whispered, \"Hey buddy this guy is your waiter and he wants your order\"\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQRP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QSPR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAnd then Gandhi came.\n\n\nP :\nGet off the backs of these peasants and workers, he told us, all you who live by their exploitation.\n\n\nQ :\nHe was like a powerful current of fresh air, like a beam of light, like a whirlwind that upset many things.\n\n\nR :\nHe spoke their language and constantly dre their attention to their appalling conditions.\n\n\nS :\nHe didn't descent from the top, he seemed to emerge from the masses of India.\n\n\nS6:\nPolitical freedom took new shape and then acquired a new content.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nBiological evolution has not fitted man to any specific environment.\n\n\nP :\nIt is by no means a biological evolution, but it is a cultural one.\n\n\nQ :\nHis imagination, his reason, his emotional subtlety and toughness, makes it possible for him not to accept the environment but to change.\n\n\nR :\nAnd that series of inventions by which man from age by age has reshaped his environment is a different kind of evolution.\n\n\nS :\nAmong the multitude of animals which scamper, burrow swim around us he is in the only one who is not locked in to his environment.\n\n\nS6:\nThat brilliant sequence of cultural peaks can most appropriately be termed the ascent of man.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe dictionary is the best friend of you task.\n\n\nP :\nThat may not be possible always.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is wise to look it up immediately.\n\n\nR :\nThen it must be firmly written on the memory and traced at the first opportunity.\n\n\nS :\nNever allow a strange word to pass unchallenged.\n\n\nS6:\nsoon you will realize that this is an exciting task.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe Bhagavadgita recognises the nature of man and the needs of man.\n\n\nP :\nAll these three aspects constitute the nature of man.\n\n\nQ :\nIt shows how the human being is rational one, an ethical one and a spiritual one.\n\n\nR :\nMore than all, it must be a spiritual experience.\n\n\nS :\nNothing can give him fulfilment unless it satisfies his reason, his ethical conscience.\n\n\nS6:\nA man whom does not harmonise them, is not truly human.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "RSPQ", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI usually sleep quite well in the train, but this time I slept only a little.\n\n\nP :\nMost people wanted it shut and I wanted it open.\n\n\nQ :\nAs usual, I got angry about the window.\n\n\nR :\nThe quarrel left me completely upset.\n\n\nS :\nThere were too many people too much huge luggage all around.\n\n\nS6:\nIt was shut all night, as usual\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIn 1934, William Golding published a small volume of poems.\n\n\nP :\nDuring the World War II(1939-45) he joined the Royal Navy and was present at the sinking of the Bismarck.\n\n\nQ :\nHe returned to teaching in 1945 and gave it up in 1962, and is now a full time writer.\n\n\nR :\nIn 1939, he married and started teaching at Vishop Wordsworth school in Salisbury.\n\n\nS :\nAt first his novels were not accepted.\n\n\nS6:\nBut the Lord of the files which came out in 1954 was welcomed as \"a most absorbing and instructive tale\".\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe future beckons to us.\n\n\nP :\nIn fact we have hard work ahead.\n\n\nQ :\nWhere do we go and what shall be our endeavour?\n\n\nR :\nWe shall also have to fight and end poverty, ignorance and disease.\n\n\nS :\nIt will be to bring freedom and oppurtunity to the common man.\n\n\nS6:\nThere is no resting for any one of us till we redeem our pledge in full.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMost of the universities in the country are now facing financial crisis.\n\n\nP :\nCost benefit yardstick thus should not be applied in the case of universities.\n\n\nQ :\nThe current state of affairs cannot be allowed to continue for long.\n\n\nR :\nUniversities cannot be equated with commercial enterprises.\n\n\nS :\nProper development of universities and colleges must be ensured.\n\n\nS6:\nThe Government should realise this before it is too late.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhile talking to a group, one should feel self-confident and courageous.\n\n\nP :\nNor is it a gift bestowed by providence on only a few.\n\n\nQ :\nOne should also learn how to think calmly and clearly.\n\n\nR :\nIt is like the ability to play golf.\n\n\nS :\nIt is not as difficult as most men imagine.\n\n\nS6:\nAny man can develop his capacity if he has  the desire to do so.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA ceiling on urban property.\n\n\nP :\nNo mill-owner could own factories or mills or plants.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd mass circulation papers\n\n\nR :\nWould mean that\n\n\nS :\nNo press magnate could own printing presses.\n\n\nS6:\nsince their value would exceed the ceiling fixed by the government.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe art of growing old is one which the passage of time has forced upon my attention.\n\n\nP :\nOne of these is undue absorption in the past.\n\n\nQ :\nOne's thought must be directed to the future and to things about which there is something to be done.\n\n\nR :\nPsychologically, there are two dangers to be guarded against in old age.\n\n\nS :\nIt does not do to live in memories, in regrets for the good old days, or in sadness about friend who are dead.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is not always easy one's own past is gradually increasing weight.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "RPSQ", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI keep on flapping my big ears all day.\n\n\nP :\nThey also fear that I will flip them all away.\n\n\nQ :\nBut children wonder why I flap them so.\n\n\nR :\nI flap them so to make sure they are safely there on either side of my head.\n\n\nS :\nBut I know what I am doing.\n\n\nS6:\nAm I not a smart, intelligent elephant?\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce King Shantnu met a young and beautiful fisher girl.\n\n\nP :\nHe went to the fisherman and asked him for her asked him for her hand in marriage.\n\n\nQ :\nThe King was extremely sad and returned to his palace.\n\n\nR :\nHe fell in love with the fisher girl.\n\n\nS :\nThe fisherman agreed to it condition that the son of his daughter should be heir to the throne of Hastinapur.\n\n\nS6:\nDevavrata, the King's son, asked him the reason of his sadness.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nReliogion is not a matter of mere dogmatic conformity.\n\n\nP :\nIt is not merely going through the ritual prescribed to us.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is not a question of ceremonial piety.\n\n\nR :\nUnless that kind of transformation occurs, you are not an authentically religious man.\n\n\nS :\nIt is the remarking of your own self, the transformation of your nature.\n\n\nS6:\nA man of that character is free from fear, free from hatred.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWe speak today of self-determination in politics.\n\n\nP :\nSo long as one is conscious of a restraint, it is possible to resist it or to near it as a necessary evil and to keep free in spirit.\n\n\nQ :\nSlavery begins when one ceases to feel that restraint and it depends on if the evil is accepted as good.\n\n\nR :\nThere is, however, a subtler domination exercised in the sphere of ideas by one culture to another.\n\n\nS :\nPolitical subjection primarily means restraint on the outer life of people.\n\n\nS6:\nCultural subjection is ordinarily of an unconscious character and it implies slavery from the very start.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "SPQR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce upon a time an ant lived on the bank of river.\n\n\nP :\nThe dove saw the ant struggling in water in a helpless condition.\n\n\nQ :\nAll its efforts to come up is failed.\n\n\nR :\nOne day it suddenly slipped in to water.\n\n\nS :\nA dove lived in the tree on the bank not far from the spot.\n\n\nS6:\nShe was touched.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe December dance and music season in Madras is like the annual tropical cyclone.\n\n\nP :\nA few among the new aspirants dazzle witht he colour of youth, like fresh saplings.\n\n\nQ :\nIt rains an abundance of music for over a fortnight.\n\n\nR :\nThick clouds expectation charge the atmosphere with voluminous advertisements.\n\n\nS :\nAt the end of it one is left with the feeling that the music of only those artists seasoned by careful nurturing, stands tall like well-routed trees.\n\n\nS6:\nMany a hastily planed shrub gets washed away in the storm.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "QRSP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is a touching story of Professor Hardy visiting Ramanujan as he lay desperately ill in hospital at Putney.\n\n\nP :\n'No Hardy, that is not a dull number in the very least.\n\n\nQ :\nHardy, who was a very shy man, could not find the words for his distress.\n\n\nR :\nIt was 1729.\n\n\nS :\nThe best he could do, as he got to the beside was \"I say Ramanujan, I thought the number of taxi I came down in was a very dull number\"\n\n\nS6:\nIt is the lowest number that can be expressed in two different ways as the sum of two cubes.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPoliteness is not a quality possessed by only one nation or race.\n\n\nP :\nOne may observe that a man of one nation will remove his hat or fold his hands by way of greetings when he meets someone he knows.\n\n\nQ :\nA man of another country will not to do so.\n\n\nR :\nIt is a quality to be found among all peoples and nations in every corner of the earth.\n\n\nS :\nObviously, each person follows the custom of his particular country.\n\n\nS6:\nIn any case, we should not mock at others habits.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "PRQS", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThroughout history man has used energy from the sun.\n\n\nP :\nToday, when we burn wood or use electric current we are drawing an energy.\n\n\nQ :\nHowever we now have a new supply of energy.\n\n\nR :\nAll our ordinary life depends on sun.\n\n\nS :\nThis has come from the sun.\n\n\nS6:\nThis energy comes from inside atoms.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThis weather-vane often tops a church spire, tower or high building.\n\n\nP :\nThey are only wind-vanes.\n\n\nQ :\nNeither alone can tell us what the weather will be.\n\n\nR :\nThey are designed to point to direction from which the wind is coming.\n\n\nS :\nJust as the barometer only tells us the pressure of air, the weather-vane tells us the direction of wind.\n\n\nS6:\nThe weather-vane can, however give us some indication of other.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nBut how does a new word get into the dictionary?\n\n\nP :\nWhen a new dictionary is being edited, a lexicographer collects all the alphabetically arranged citation slips for a particular word.\n\n\nQ :\nThe dictionary makers notice it and make a note of it on a citation slip.\n\n\nR :\nThe moment new word is coined, it usually enter the spoken language.\n\n\nS :\nThe word then passes from the realm of hearing to the realm of writing.\n\n\nS6:\nHe sorts them according to their grammatical function, and carefully writes a definition.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nGrowing up means not only getting larger, but also using our sense and our brain is to become more aware of things around us.\n\n\nP :\nNot only does he have a memory but he is able to think and reason.\n\n\nQ :\nIn this, man differs from all other animals.\n\n\nR :\nBefore we spray our roadside plants or turn sewage in to our rivers, we should pause to think what the results of our action are likely to do.\n\n\nS :\nThis is to say, he is able to plan what he is is going to do in the light of his experience before he does it.\n\n\nS6:\nIn other words, we must develop and use our ability to reason, because the destruction or the preservation of the places in which we live depend on us.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "SPRQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nJawaharlal Nehru was the greatest plan-enthusiast.\n\n\nP :\nUnder Nehru's advice, the pre-Independent congress set up National Planning Commission in 1938.\n\n\nQ :\nBut he forgot that what could be achieved by force under the communist dictatorship of Russia was not possible under the democratic set up of India.\n\n\nR :\nHe took the idea from Russia where Five year plans transformed a very backward country into a top power of the world.\n\n\nS :\nNo free government can call for compulsory sacrifice and suffering from the whole people.\n\n\nS6:\nNehru himself became the chairman of the commission.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "RQSP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nDuryodhana was a wicked prince.\n\n\nP :\none day Bhima made Duryodhana fall from a tree from which Duryodhana was stealing fruits.\n\n\nQ :\nHe did not like that Pandavas should be loved and respected by the people of Hastinapur\n\n\nR :\nDuryodhana specially hated Bhima.\n\n\nS :\nAmong the Pandavas, Bhima was extraordinary strong and powerful\n\n\nS6:\nThis enraged Duryodhana so much that he began to think of removing Bhima from his way.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nJawaharlal Nehru was born in Allahabad on 14 Nov 1889.\n\n\nP :\nNehru meet Mahatma Gandhi in February 1920.\n\n\nQ :\nIn 1905 he was sent to London to study at a school called Haroow.\n\n\nR :\nHe became the first Prime Minister of Independent India on 15 August 1947.\n\n\nS :\nHe married Kamla Kaul in 1915.\n\n\nS6:\nHe died on 27 May 1964.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "RPQS", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIt was a dark moonless night.\n\n\nP :\nHe turned over the pages, reading passages here and there.\n\n\nQ :\nHe heard them on the floor.\n\n\nR :\nThe poet took down his books of poems from his shelves.\n\n\nS :\nSome of them contained his earliest writings which he had almost forgotten.\n\n\nS6:\nThey all seemed to him to be poor and ordinary mere childish words.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI had halted on the road.\n\n\nP :\nAs soon as I saw the elephant I knew I should not shoot him.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is a serious matter to shoot a working elephant.\n\n\nR :\nI knew that his 'must' was already passing off.\n\n\nS :\nThe elephant was standing 8 yards from the road.\n\n\nS6:\nI decided to watch him for a while and then go home.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPQR", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is only one monkey we can thoroughly recommend as an indoor pet.\n\n\nP :\nThey quickly die from colds and coughs after the first winter fogs.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is beautiful and intelligent Capuchin monkey.\n\n\nR :\nThe lively little Capuchins, however, may be left for years in an English house without the least danger to their health.\n\n\nS :\nThe Marmosets, it is true, are more beautiful than a Capuchins and just as pleasing, but they are too delicate for the English climate\n\n\nS6:\nFinally let me say that no other monkey has a better temper or winning ways.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA man can be physically confined within stone walls.\n\n\nP :\nBut his mind and spirit will still be free.\n\n\nQ :\nThus his freedom of action may be restricted.\n\n\nR :\nHis hopes and aspiration still remain with him.\n\n\nS :\nHence, he will be free spiritually if not physically.\n\n\nS6:\nNo tyranny can intimidate a lover of liberty.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce upon atime there lived three young men in a certain town of Hindustan.\n\n\nP :\nAll the people of the neighbourhood were mortally afraid of them.\n\n\nQ :\nThey were so powerful that they could catch growing lions and tear them to pieces.\n\n\nR :\nSomeone told them that they would become immortal if they killed Death.\n\n\nS :\nThe young men believed themselves to be very good friends.\n\n\nS6:\nAll of them set out in search of their foe called Death.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMetals are today being replaced by polymers in many applications.\n\n\nP :\nAbove all, they are cheaper and easier to process making them a viable alternative to metals.\n\n\nQ :\nPolymers are essentially a long chains of hydrocarbon molecules.\n\n\nR :\nToday polymers as strong as metals have been developed.\n\n\nS :\nThese have replaced the traditional chromium-plated metallic bumpers in cars.\n\n\nS6:\nMany Indian Institutes of science and Technology run special programmes on polymer science.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSince the sixties there has been an increasing interest in neurophysiology, which deals with the neural bases of mental activity and behaviour.\n\n\nP :\nIt has format which is very similar to that of Brain and Language, a sister journal.\n\n\nQ :\nSince then, a number of journals devoted entirely to this area of research have appeared.\n\n\nR :\nBefore the 1960's when this field was the concern of a small number of investigators, research articles were scattered in various neurological journals.\n\n\nS :\nBrain and cognition is one such journal.\n\n\nS6:\nSo far the journal has published the mixture of articles including reports and investigations.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAn elderly lady suddenly became blind.\n\n\nP :\nThe doctor called daily and every time he took away some of her furniture he liked.\n\n\nQ :\nAt last she was cured and the doctor demanded his fee.\n\n\nR :\nShe agreed to pay a large fee to the doctor who would cure her\n\n\nS :\nOn being refused, the doctor wanted to know the reason.\n\n\nS6:\nThe lady said that she had not been properly cured because she could not see all his furniture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhat are the causes of our chronic food shortage ?\n\n\nP :\nTo find for these growing new millions is desperate task.\n\n\nQ :\nevery year, we add more than a crore of persons to our population.\n\n\nR :\nDespite stupendous efforts by our government, the population is growing unabated.\n\n\nS :\nThe chief cause is the population explosion.\n\n\nS6:\nThis unprecedented growth can drag us to the doors of starvation very soon.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOur ancestors thought that anything which moved itself was alive.\n\n\nP :\nThe philosopher Descartes thought that both men and animals were machines.\n\n\nQ :\nBut a machine such as a motorcar or a steamship moves itself, as soon as machines which moved themselves had been made, people asked \"Is man a machine?\"\n\n\nR :\nAnd before the days of machinery that was a good definition.\n\n\nS :\nHe also thought that the human machine was partly controlled by the soul action on a certain part of the brain, while animals had no souls.\n\n\nS6:\nTherefore some scientists think that life is just a very complicated mechanism.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPayment for imports and exports is made through a system called foreign exchange.\n\n\nP :\nThe value of the money of one country in relation to the money of other countries is agreed upon.\n\n\nQ :\nThese rates of exchange vary from time to time.\n\n\nR :\nFor instance, an American dollar or a British pound sterling is worth certain amounts in the money of other countries.\n\n\nS :\nSometimes a United States dollar is worth 12 pesos in Mexico.\n\n\nS6:\nAnother time it may be worth eight pesos.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "PRQS", "optd": "RPQS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMoncure Conway devoted his life to two great objects freedom of thought, and freedom of the individual.\n\n\nP :\nThey threaten both kinds of freedom.\n\n\nQ :\nBut something also has been lost.\n\n\nR :\nThere are now dangers, somewhat different in form from those of the past ages.\n\n\nS :\nIn regard to both these objects, something has been gained since his time.\n\n\nS6:\nUnless a vigorous and vigilant public opinion can be aroused in defence of them, there will be much less of both a hundred years hence then there is now.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe study of speech disorders due to brain injury suggests that patients can think without having adequate control over their language.\n\n\nP :\nBut they succeed in playing games of chess.\n\n\nQ :\nSome patients, for example fail to find the names of objects presented to them.\n\n\nR :\nThey can even use the concepts needed for chess playing, though they are unable to express many of the concepts in ordinary language.\n\n\nS :\nThey even find it difficult to interpret long written notices.\n\n\nS6:\nHow they manage to do this we do not know.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA black haired, young woman came tripping along.\n\n\nP :\nShe was leading a young woman wearing a hat.\n\n\nQ :\nThe woman swept it off and tossed it in the air.\n\n\nR :\nThe child jumped up to catch the hat.\n\n\nS :\nThe young man tossed his head to shake the hat back.\n\n\nS6:\nBoth disappeared from view.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWe now know that the oceans are very deep.\n\n\nP :\nFor example, the Indian ocean has a range called the Indian Ridge.\n\n\nQ :\nMuch of it is fairly flat.\n\n\nR :\nHowever, there are great mountain ranges as well.\n\n\nS :\nOn average the bottom is 2.5 miles to 3.5 miles down\n\n\nS6:\nThis reaches from the India to the Antarctic.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMinnie went shopping one morning.\n\n\nP :\nDisappointed She turned around and returned to the parking lot.\n\n\nQ :\nShe got out and walked to the nearest shop.\n\n\nR :\nShe drove her car into the parking lot and stopped.\n\n\nS :\nIt was there that she realised that she'd forgotten her purse at home.\n\n\nS6:\nShe drove home with an empty basket.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFar away in a little street there is a poor house.\n\n\nP :\nHer face is thin and worn and her hands are coarse, pricked by a needle, for she is a seam stress.\n\n\nQ :\nOne of the windows is open and through it I can see a poor woman.\n\n\nR :\nHe has a fever and asking for oranges.\n\n\nS :\nIn a bed in a corner of the room her little boy is lying ill.\n\n\nS6:\nHis mother has nothing to give but water, so he is crying.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA noise started above their heads.\n\n\nP :\nBut people did not take it seriously.\n\n\nQ :\nThat was to show everyone that there was something wrong\n\n\nR :\nIt was a dangerous thing to do.\n\n\nS :\nFor, within minutes the ship began to sink.\n\n\nS6:\nNearly 200 lives were lost on the fateful day.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "PRQS", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAmerican private lies may seem shallow.\n\n\nP :\nStudents would walk away with books they had not paid for.\n\n\nQ :\nA Chinese journalist commented on a curious institution: the library\n\n\nR :\nTheir public morality, however, impressed visitors.\n\n\nS :\nBut in general they returned them.\n\n\nS6:\nThis would not happen in china, he said.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe path of Venus lies inside the path of the Earth.\n\n\nP :\nWhen at its farthest from the Earth, Venus is 160 million away\n\n\nQ :\nWith such a wide range between its greatest and leat distances it is natural that at sometimes Venus appears much brighter than at others.\n\n\nR :\nNo other body ever comes so near the Earth, with the exception of the Moon and occasional comet or asteroid.\n\n\nS :\nWhen Venus is at its nearest to the earth it is only 26 million miles away.\n\n\nS6:\nWhen at its brightest, it is easily seen with the naked eye in broad daylight.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIn India marriages are usually arranged by parents\n\n\nP :\nSometimes boys and girls do not like th idea of arranged marriages.\n\n\nQ :\nMost young people accepts the state of affairs.\n\n\nR :\nShanta was like that.\n\n\nS :\nThey assume their parents can make good choices.\n\n\nS6:\nShe felt she was a modern girl and not subject for bargaining.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nShe said on the phone that she would report for duty next day.\n\n\nP :\nWe waited for few days then we decided to go to her place.\n\n\nQ :\nBut she did not.\n\n\nR :\nwe found it locked.\n\n\nS :\nEven after that we waited for her quite a few days.\n\n\nS6:\nEventually we reported to the police.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSeveral sub-cities have been planned around capital.\n\n\nP :\nDwarga is the first among them.\n\n\nQ :\nThey are expected to alleviate the problem of housing.\n\n\nR :\nIt is coming up in the south west of capital.\n\n\nS :\nIt will cater to over one million people when completed.\n\n\nS6:\nHopefully the housing problem will not be as acute at present after these sub-cities are built.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "QRSP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nForecasting the weather has always been a difficult business.\n\n\nP :\nDuring a period of drought, streams and rivers dried up, the cattle died from thirst and were ruined.\n\n\nQ :\nMany different things affect the weather and we have to study them carefully to make accurate forecast.\n\n\nR :\nAncient Egyptians had no need of weather in the  Nile Valley hardly ever changes.\n\n\nS :\nIn early times, when there were no instruments, such as thermometer or the barometer, man looked for tell-tale signs in the sky.\n\n\nS6:\nHe made his forecasts by watching flights of the birds or the way smoke rose from fire.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRQS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAs he passed beneath her he heard the swish of her wings.\n\n\nP :\nHe was not falling head long now.\n\n\nQ :\nThe monstrous terror seized him.\n\n\nR :\nBut it only lasted a minute.\n\n\nS :\nHe could hear nothing.\n\n\nS6:\nThe next moment he felt his wings spread outwards.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMs. Parasuram started a Petrol Pump in Madras.\n\n\nP :\nA total to 12 girls now work at the pump.\n\n\nQ :\nShe advertised in newspapers for women staff.\n\n\nR :\nThey operate in 2 shifts.\n\n\nS :\nThe response was good.\n\n\nS6:\nThus she has shown the way for many others.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSun birds are among the smallest of Indian birds.\n\n\nP :\nThough they are functionally similar to the humming birds of the New World, they are totally unrelated.\n\n\nQ :\nThey do eat insects too.\n\n\nR :\nThey are also some of the most brilliantly coloured birds.\n\n\nS :\nsun birds feed on nectar mostly and helped in pollination.\n\n\nS6:\nOur common sun birds are the purple sun bird, the glossy black species and purple rumped sun bird, the yellow and maroon species.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFor decades, American society has been calling a melting pot\n\n\nP :\nDifferences remained - in appearence, mannerisms, customs, speech, religion and more.\n\n\nQ :\nThe term has long been a cliche and half-truth.\n\n\nR :\nBut homogenisation was never acheived.\n\n\nS :\nYes, immigrants from diverse cultures and traditions did cast off vestiges of their native lands and become almost imperceptibly woven in to the American fabric.\n\n\nS6:\nIn recent years, such differences accentuated by the arrival of immigrants from Asia and other parts of the world in the United States - have become something to celebrate and to nurture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI took cigarettes from my case.\n\n\nP :\nBut when the fit of coughing was over, he replaced it between his lips.\n\n\nQ :\nI lit one of them and placed it between the lips.\n\n\nR :\nThen with a feeble hand he removed the cigarette.\n\n\nS :\nSlowly he took a pull at it and coughed violently.\n\n\nS6:\nThen he continues to draw on it.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is difference between Gandhiji's concept of secularism and that of Nehru's.\n\n\nP :\nNehru's idea of secularism was equal indifference to all religions and bothering about none of them.\n\n\nQ :\nAccording to Gandhiji, all religions are equally true and each scripture is worthy of respect.\n\n\nR :\nSuch secularism which means the rejection of all religions is contrary to our culture and tradition.\n\n\nS :\nIn Gandhiji's view, secularism stands for equal respect for all religions.\n\n\nS6:\nInstead of doing any good, such secularism can do harm instead of good.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\n As a dramatist Rabindranath was not what might be called a success.\n\n\nP :\nHis dramas were moulded on the lines of the traditional Indian village dramas than the dramas of modern world.\n\n\nQ :\nHis plays were more a catalogue of ideas than a vehicle of the expression of action.\n\n\nR :\nActually the drama has always been the life of Indian people, as it deals with legends of gods and goddesses.\n\n\nS :\nAlthough in his short stories and novels he was able to create living and well defined characters, he did not seem to be able to do so in dramas\n\n\nS6:\nTherefor, drama forms the essential part of the traditional Indian Culture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIt is regrettable that there is widespread corruption in the country at all levels.\n\n\nP :\nSo there is hardly anything that the government can do about it now.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd there are graft and other malpractices too.\n\n\nR :\nThe impression that corruption is universal phenomenon persists and the people not cooperate in checking this evil.\n\n\nS :\nRecently several offenders were brought to book, but they were not given deterrent punishment.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is indeed a tragedy of great magnitude.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe heart is pump of life.\n\n\nP :\nThey have even succeeded in heart transplants.\n\n\nQ :\nNowadays surgeons are able to stop a patients heart and carry out complicated operations.\n\n\nR :\nA few years ago it was impossible to operate on a patient whose heart was not working properly.\n\n\nS :\nIf heart stops we die in about five minutes.\n\n\nS6:\nAll this was made possible by the invention of heart-lung machine.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nYour letter was big relief.\n\n\nP :\nHow did you exams go?\n\n\nQ :\nAfter your result, you must come here for a week.\n\n\nR :\nYou hadn't written for over a month.\n\n\nS :\nI am sure you will come out with flying colours.\n\n\nS6:\nBut don't forget to bring chocolate for Geetha.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RPSQ", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}